William Mansfield Clark Papers 1903-1964 Mss.B.C547
American Philosophical Society
William Mansfield Clark Papers
1903-1964
Mss.B.C547
American Philosophical Society
7.75 Linear feet
A long-time member of the faculty at Johns Hopkins, the biochemist William Mansfield Clark made significant contributions to the understanding of oxidation-reduction potentials of organic systems. This collection of Clark's professional papers includes drafts of manuscripts and correspondence, especially with James B. Conant and Barnett Cohen, relating to Clark's life and research. Of particular note are Clark's Cutter lectures at Harvard in 1930 and his correspondence with Eric G. Ball, when Ball worked in Otto Warburg's lab in Berlin in 1937-1938. Clark's participation in professional organizations is reflected in correspondence with the Society of American Bacteriologists and with the Journal of Biological Chemistry, as well as with colleagues Stanley Benedict and Rudolph Anderson. There is some material relating to Clark's lectures and papers, and there are four student notebooks (physical chemistry, optics, thermodynamics/physics), and twenty-three miscellaneous scientific notebooks, 1941-1953.
Clark, W. Mansfield (William Mansfield), 1884-1964
General note
H. B. Vickery, "William Mansfield Clark," National Academy of Sciences, Biographical Memoirs 39:1-36 (includes bibliography). Another biographical treatment is found in the APS Yearbook 1965:116-120.
William M. Clark, "Notes on a Half-Century of Research, Teaching and Administration," Annual Review of Biochemistry 31 (1962).
Clark, "Notes on a Half-Century of Research, Teaching and Administration," 11.
General note
AAAS
American Association for the Advancement of Science
ACS
American Chemical Society
JHU
Johns Hopkins University
NAS
National Academy of Sciences
NRC
National Research Council
US
United States
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
William Mansfield Clark headed the Department of Physiological Chemistry at the Johns Hopkins Medical School from 1927 to 1952, where he developed a major research program in physical biochemistry, centering around oxidation-reduction potentials of organic systems, research that required precise measurements and sensitive instruments. The Clark Papers contain material relating to his lectures and papers, twenty-four notebooks (1941-1953), ten files on his associate Barnett Cohen (1910s-1950s) that include extensive data on dyes, and two photograph files containing pictures of his laboratory, the "Temple of pH." There are also four student notebooks (physical chemistry, optics, thermodynamics/physics), which together with the correspondence, form a rich record on laboratory practice and training in physical biochemistry.
Before coming to Johns Hopkins, Clark had worked in bacterial chemistry at the United States Department of Agriculture and in the United States Public Health Service, where he was made chief of the Division of Chemistry of the Hygienic Laboratory. A few files (records dated before 1927) contain information on the practice of biochemistry and microbiology within federal bureaus.
Clark's career, as seen from his papers, exemplifies the disciplinary evolution from medical chemistry to biochemistry. As the founders of American biochemistry sought to liberate their field from a clinical service role, they increasingly allied it with the physical sciences; Clark's skills in physical biochemistry -- his hydrogen ion determinations, and his studies of buffers and salts in connection with bacterial fermentation--were well suited to the new orientation.
During his tenure at Johns Hopkins, Clark assumed leadership of his profession. He was on the editorial board of the Journal of Biological Chemistry and served as president of both the Society of American Bacteriologists and the American Society of Biological Chemists.
Series I. Correspondence:
Abel, John Jacob, 1857-1938 ( Indicative of the early evolution of American biochemistry, as a field evolving from a clinical-service role to a field increasingly allied with the physical sciences. Located within the Johns Hopkins University Medical School correspondence.) Correspondence (2 items) 1927 English
Adams, Roger, 1889-1971 ( Poem entitled "An Ode to the CMR" [Committee on Medical Research].) Manuscripts (1 item) 1945 English
American Society of Biological Chemists ( Documents important institutional aspects of the rise of American biochemistry.) Correspondence (24 items) 1931-1957 English
Anderson, Rudolph John, 1879-1961 ( Matters related to Clark's editorship of the Journal of Biological Chemistry. Located within the Journal of Biological Chemistry and ACS New York Section, William H. Nichols Medal correspondence.) Correspondence (35 items) 1936-1957 English
Ball, Eric Glendinning, 1904-1979 ( Illuminates interesting aspects of Ball's scientific career, the intellectual content and institutional settings. The most valuable part of the correspondence are the letters written from Europe when Ball was on sabbatical leave in 1937-1938. Most of the letters are about Otto Warburg's laboratory at the Kaiser-Wilhelm Institute in Berlin, where Ball was working on determinations of oxidation-reduction potentials in the cytochrome system. These letters offer a wealth of information on the physical aspects of the laboratory, social interactions, and Warburg's personality. There are also descriptions of Ball's stay at the Harnack-Haus and his reaction to the political scene in Germany. Also reveal episodes and attitudes (including anti-Semitism) related to the intellectual migration.) Correspondence (26 items) 1937-1963 English
Bowman, Isaiah, 1878-1950 ( Shows Clark to have been an active member of the scientific establishment that emerged after World War I and shaped American science well into the 1950s. Located within the the following folders: ACS New York Section, William H. Nichols Medal; Johns Hopkins University; Bowman, Isaiah, Series II.) Correspondence (14 items) 1936-1949 English
Bronk, Detlev W. (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975 ( Shows Clark to have been an active member of the scientific establishment that emerged after World War I and shaped American science well into the 1950s.) Correspondence (5 items) 1948-1952, n.d. English
Bush, Vannevar, 1890-1974 ( Shows Clark to have been an active member of the scientific establishment that emerged after World War I and shaped American science well into the 1950s. Located within the following folders: NRC Antimalarial Drug Program; National Resources Planning Board; Office of Scientific Research and Development.) Correspondence (27 items) 1941-1945 English
Cannan, R. Keith ( Reflections on Clark's program and his place within biochemistry.) Correspondence (20 items) 1924-1931, 1955, n.d. English
Cannon, Walter B. (Walter Bradford), 1871-1945 ( Administrative communications. Located within the National Academy of Sciences Correspondence.) Correspondence (3 items) 1928, 1937 English
Conant, James Bryant, 1893-1978 ( Technical correspondence. Shows Clark to have been an active member of the scientific establishment that emerged after World War I and shaped American science well into the 1950s.) Correspondence (10 items) 1923-1941 English
Du Vigneaud, Vincent, 1901-1978 Correspondence (2 items) 1958 English
Herriott, Roger M. (Roger Moss), 1908-1992 Correspondence (4 items) 1948-1952 English
Johns Hopkins University ( Documents important institutional aspects of the rise of American biochemistry.) Correspondence (4 folders) 1909-1963 English
Loeb, Jacques, 1859-1924 ( Scientific and administrative correspondence. Illustrates Loeb's influence among biochemists and chemists.) Correspondence (3 items) 1920-1922 English
Michaelis, Leonor, 1875-1949 ( Professional exchanges.) Correspondence (8 items) 1920-1924, 1943-1950 German
Needham, Joseph, 1900-1995 Correspondence (4 items) 1925-1926 English
Noyes, W. Albert (William Albert), 1898-1980 Correspondence (2 items) 1953 English
Park, Edwards A. (Edwards Albert), 1877-1969 ( Reveals episodes and attitudes (including anti-Semitism) related to the intellectual migration. Includes material related to a dinner in honor of Park. Located in the following folders: Johns Hopkins University Medical School; Park, Edwards, Series II; Park, Edwards, Series VI.) Correspondence (6 items) 1936-1938 English
Richards, Alfred N. (Alfred Newton), 1876-1966 ( Administrative correspondence. Shows Clark to have been an active member of the scientific establishment that emerged after World War I and shaped American science well into the 1950s.) Correspondence (1 item) 1950 English
Society of American Bacteriologists ( Documents important institutional aspects of the rise of American biochemistry.) Correspondence (6 folders) 1925-1959 English
Sorensen, S. P. L. (Soren Peter Lauritz), 1868-1939 Correspondence (2 items) 1924, 1928 English
Stanley, Wendell M. (Wendell Meredith), 1904-1971 ( Located within the University of California (Berkeley), Virus Laboratory correspondence.) Correspondence (2 items) 1952 English
Theorell, Hugo Correspondence (6 items) 1952-1954, n.d. English
Unidentified ( Letter concerns Clark's appointment. Indicative of the early evolution of American biochemistry, as a field evolving from a clinical-service role to a field increasingly allied with the physical sciences.) Correspondence (1 letter) 1927 English
United States. Dept. of Agriculture ( Information on the practice of biochemistry and microbiology within federal bureaus.) Correspondence (27 items) 1910-1944, n.d. English
United States. Public Health Service ( Information on the practice of biochemistry and microbiology within federal bureaus.) Correspondence (14 items) 1920-1926, 1947 English
University of Pennsylvania ( Correspondence with William Pepper and Alfred N. Richards, indicative of the early evolution of American biochemistry, as a field evolving from a clinical-service role to a field increasingly allied with the physical sciences.) Correspondence (3 items) 1921 English
Van Slyke, Donald D. (Donald Dexter), 1883-1971 ( Scientific and administrative correspondence. Reflects the common ground (intellectual and institutional) between Clark's research on physiological equilibria and the studies of Van Slyke, and their long-term professional association.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1923-1955 English
Vickery, Hubert Bradford, 1893-1978 ( Scientific and administrative communications.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1949-1952 English
Warburg, Otto Heinrich, 1883-1970 ( Reveals episodes and attitudes (including anti-Semitism) related to the intellectual migration.) Correspondence (6 items) 1937, 1948 German
Wieland, H. (Heinrich), b. 1877 Correspondence (1 item) 1926 German
Series III. Research notes:
Cohen, Barnett, 1891-1952. "Data on Dyes" ( Extensive data on dyes. Notes and calculations made by Clark and Cohen.) Research Notes (6 folders) 1927-1951 English
Additional Biographical Notes:
Eric G. Ball received his doctorate at the University of Pennsylvania in 1930. From 1933 until 1940 he was a research associate in Clark's biochemistry laboratory at The Johns Hopkins Medical School, where he concentrated on studies of biological oxidations and enzymatic reactions under hormonal influence. These areas remained dominant in his research program at Harvard Medical School (from 1941), where he was professor of biological chemistry and chairman of the Division of Medical Sciences (1952-1962).
Separated Materials note
Most reprints have been transferred to the printed materials department of the library. If a reprint was found as an enclosure, a photocopy of the title page was filed in its place in the folder. In cases where a reprint existed in multiple copies, or was significantly annotated, it was left in the collection. To retrieve reprints removed from the collection, consult the card catalog for printed materials
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Clark Papers were donated by Miriam G. Clark in 1977 (Acc. no. 1977-1203ms) after initial contact with the Survey of Sources for the History of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, a joint committee of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, and the American Philosophical Society. An addition to the collection was donated in 1980 by Miriam G. Clark and her sister, Harriet Clark Gladding, and presented by John T. Edsall on 29 June 1982 (Acc. no. 1982-861ms). Edsall wrote brief reports surveying the material in each donation. The papers donated in 1977 were originally processed by the Library prior to the receipt of the 1980 donation. The second donation, which contained material similar in form and content to the first donation, remained unprocessed until 1996, when both donations were integrated and processed according to current Library practice.
Scope and Contents note
The William Mansfield Clark Papers (1903-1964) contain correspondence; subject files; research notes by Clark; calendars, engagement books, and appointment notes; manuscripts of published and unpublished works by Clark; manuscripts and research notes by colleagues; and photographs documenting Clark's career as a biochemist.
The papers (17 boxes; 7.5 linear feet) are divided into six series:
Series I Correspondence: 1903-1964 (7 boxes; 3.50 linear feet)
Series II Subject Files: 1903-1963 (2 boxes; 1.00 linear feet)
Series III Research Notes, Notebooks, and Calendars: 1907-1962 (3 boxes; 1.25 linear feet)
Series IV Works by Clark: 1917-1963 (3 boxes; 1.25 linear feet)
Series V Works by Others: 1921-[1952] (1 box; 0.25 linear feet)
Series VI Photographs: 1929-1945 (1 box; 0.25 linear feet)
Cross referencing to oversized material appears in the container lists of this finding aid. Photographs and negatives have been removed from Series I-V and placed in Series VI. Cross references for photographs appear in the original series.
Biographical/Historical note
A pioneer in the field of biochemistry, William Mansfield Clark (1884-1964) was born on August 17, 1884, the only son of Caroline Scoville Hopson (1840-1928) and James Starr Clark (1822-1914), an Episcopal minister from Tivoli Township, New York. The Clarks endowed William and his sisters Margaret, also known as "Daisy" (who later married the biologist Francis B. Sumner), and Anna with an exceptional education. William Clark was first educated first at the Trinity School, which his father had founded and administered, and after receiving a scholarship, he graduated from the Hotchkiss School in 1903. At Williams College, he studied under Leverett Mears, and received a B.A. and M.A. in 1907 and 1908 respectively, before moving to Johns Hopkins as a student of Harmon Morse. Clark received his PhD in 1910 for a dissertation entitled, "A Contribution to the Investigation of the Temperature Coefficient of Osmotic Pressure: A Redetermination of the Osmotic Pressures of Cane Sugar Solutions at 20°." While at Hopkins, Clark spent his summers at the recently established chemistry laboratory at Wood's Hole, Mass., where he served as the assistant to Carl Alsberg and later, Donald D. Van Slyke.
Clark's first professional position came as a research chemist with the Dairy Division of the Bureau of Animal Industry, United States Department of Agriculture, working under the direction of Lore A. Rogers. Before he resigned in June 1920, Clark worked on a variety of problems in dairy bacteriology, and, with his colleague Herbert A. Lubs, started studies in hydrogen-ion concentration. It was through these studies that Clark and Lubs developed and defined the concept of pH, resulting in Clark's seminal book, The Determination of Hydrogen Ions (1920, 1923, 1928). H. B. Vickery writes of the book, "[it] brought about what amounted to a revolution in bacteriological laboratories and exerted a profound influence upon all aspects of biochemistry where the measurement and control of acidity are matters of importance." 1
Remaining in the government service, Clark took a position at the Hygiene Laboratory of the U.S. Public Health Service in July, 1920, where he remained until 1927. As had been the case at the Dairy Division, Clark was given wide latitude in pursuing his research interests, which, as Clark himself wrote, increasingly focused "in measurements of oxidation-reduction potentials and their systematic formulation." 2 Clark and others undertook the reporting of their findings in a series of papers entitled, "Studies on Oxidation-Reduction," many of which were co-authored with his long-time friend and colleague Barnett Cohen. The first of these articles was published in 1923, the last, number 24, in 1956.
Clark continued his research into oxidation-reduction potentials when he accepted an appointment as DeLamar Professor of Physiological Chemistry at Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine. During his 25 years at Hopkins, from 1927 to 1952, Clark expanded his research program into ligand and metalloporphyrin systems, and he developed the concept of a "chemical continuum." In addition to laboratory research, he carried a full load of teaching and administrative responsibilities.
By all accounts, Clark was much respected as both a teacher and administrator. His desire to provide his medical students with a proper background in chemistry led him to write the enormously successful textbook, Topics in Physical Chemistry (1948, 1952). Clark clearly valued his teaching duties, writing, "[t]houghtful easement of the acquirement of knowledge is an essential part of the economics and of the aesthetics of education. It should not be regarded as less than among the tougher of intellectual jobs." 3 In addition to teaching, writing, and conducting research, Clark served on the editorial board of the Journal of Biological Chemistry from 1933 until 1952.
During World War II, Clark served as chair of the Division of Chemistry and Chemical Technology, National Research Council; was a consultant to both the Committee on Medical Research of the Office of Scientific Research and Development, and the National Defense Research Committee; was chair, and later a member, of the Committee on Biological Warfare, National Academy of Sciences; a member of the Committee on Quartermaster Problems, National Academy of Sciences; and a member of the National Academy of Sciences Council. Among the more important developments emerging from Clarks's frenzied wartime activity was the testing and development of antimalarial agents for the U.S. military. As a member of the Board for the Coordination of Malaria Studies, Clark was heavily involved in testing the most successful agent of the time, quinacrine, and in searching for new antimalarial compounds.
In 1952, Clark retired from Hopkins and was appointed DeLamar Emeritus Professor and Research Professor of Chemistry. Succeeded as the DeLamar Professor by Albert Lehninger, Clark moved from his laboratory at the medical school to one on the university's Homewood campus, where he continued his research, while maintaining a regular schedule of publication and teaching. His last book, Oxidation-Reduction Potentials of Organic Systems, appeared in 1960. Clark was working on a revision at this book, an exhaustive survey of research in the field, at the time of his death in Baltimore on January 19, 1964. He was survived by two daughters, Harriet Allen (Mrs. Everett B. Gladding) and Miriam Clark, from his marriage, on 14 September 1910, to Rose Willard Goddard (d. 1958).
Clark received a number of honors and awards during his career, including election to the National Academy of Sciences (1928) and the American Philosophical Society (1939); election as President of the Society of American Bacteriologists and of the American Society of Biological Chemists (1933 and 1934); and selection for the Cutter Lectures on Preventive Medicine (1930), as Harvey Lecturer (Fall 1933); and as Remsen Memorial Lecturer (1952). He received honorary degrees from Williams College (1935) and the University of Pennsylvania (1940), and was awarded the William H. Nichols Medal of the New York Section, American Chemical Society (1936), the Borden Award (1944); the President's Certificate of Merit (1948); the Passano Award (1957); and the Award of Merit of the Maryland Section, American Chemical Society (1963).
Clark, Miriam G.; Gladding, Harriet Clark; Antimalarials--Research--United States; Bacteriologists; Bacteriology--Societies, etc.; Bacteriology.; Biochemistry.; Biochemists--France; Biochemists--Germany; Biochemists--Great Britain; Biochemists--United States; Chemistry--Societies, etc.; Hydrogen-ion concentration; Journal of Bacteriology; Journal of Biological Chemistry; Malaria--Chemotherapy; Medicine--Research--United States; Medicine--Study and teaching; Oxidation, Physiological; Quinacrine
- Series I. Correspondence, 1903-1964; 3.5 lin. feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Incoming and outgoing manuscript and typescript letters, and carbons generated during Clark's career. There are also a small number of memoranda, telegrams, postcards, and one piece of V-mail. Series I is arranged alphabetically by correspondent's name and then, unless otherwise noted in the container listing, chronologically within each folder.
  When a correspondence file includes letters to a third party (i.e., not Clark), or features significant references to other individuals, the name of the person is indicated on the container list by the use of an indent under the folder title.
  An effort was made to file the correspondence generated as a result Clark's activities in of institutional business and administration under the name of the organization. Notes were made of the individuals generating the letters, and they are also indicated by indenting the individual's name beneath that of the organization (i.e., the folder heading).
  Unidentified correspondence has been filed as "Unidentified" and is arranged chronologically. Enclosed manuscripts have generally been removed from this series and placed in Series III or IV as appropriate. As with reprints, a photocopy of the title page was filed with the original letter. Letters of reference are filed under the name of the person who is the subject of the letter. Extensive cross references have been made between material in Series I to related items in other folders in the series, and to related items in Series II-VI.
  The bulk of this series covers the 1920s through 1963. Correspondents include bacteriologists, biochemists, chemists, medical doctors, students, and publishers; as well as family and friends. Among the topics covered in this series are: research on acid-base indicators and pH; oxidation-reduction, chiefly in biological systems; the U.S. Government's programs devoted to antimalarial drug research during World War II; lectures, symposia and conferences; the editing and publishing of journal articles and books; and participation in professional and learned societies. In particular, there is correspondence documenting Clark's work at the U.S. Department of Agriculture, U.S. Public Health Service, the Johns Hopkins University, and the National Academy of Sciences / National Research Council. Also filed here are a number of interesting letters (1937-38) to Clark from Eric G. Ball while Ball was working in Otto Warburg's lab at the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute. Clark's service to the American Society of Biological Chemists, the Society of American Bacteriologists, and the journals of each society is also illustrated.
  Correspondents in Series I include:
  American Chemical Society (ACS)
  American Society of Biological Chemists
  Anderson, Rudolph J.
  Ball, Eric G.
  Benedict, Stanley R.
  Bronk, Detlev W.
  Bush, Vannevar
  Cannan, R. Keith
  Chesney, Alan
  Chinard, Francis P.
  Cohen, Barnett
  Conant, James B.
  Cowgill, Robert W.
  du Vigneaud, Vincent
  Fruton, Joseph S.
  Harbury, Henry
  Hastings, A. Baird
  The Hotchkiss School
  Jewett, Frank B.
  Johns Hopkins University